<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-08-23T11:31:44+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">SoftwareBear</title><subtitle>Keep track of my ramblings throughout the software wilderness</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A bit of zest on X-Macro</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/08/23/a-bit-of-zest-on-x-macro.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A bit of zest on X-Macro" /><published>2018-08-23T09:40:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-08-23T09:40:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/08/23/a-bit-of-zest-on-x-macro</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/08/23/a-bit-of-zest-on-x-macro.html">&lt;p&gt;Back in 1994 I came across a technique of generating C++ code through Macros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Macros in modern C++ are generally avoided like the plague by developers these days … but they still have their uses even in modern code … especially when memory is tight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve used this pattern many times over the years but I have never had a name for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A colleague asked me to review some of their code the other day and I was surprised to see something very similar to the pattern I knew … except I was stumped for a moment or two as to how it worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My colleague was using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X_Macro&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;X Macro&lt;/a&gt; technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My difficulty with the code was … where is X defined … I was scouring the list of #includes and the files to find it … but I couldn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it dawned on me that it would just use X when instantiated and X would be replaced if it was also #defined somewhere … then I searched for definitions of macro X … low and behold I found loads of #defines and #undef of X all over the place along with lots of comments explaining what is happening … because X is not a very discriptive name for a macro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It works obviously … but it was not the refined technique I knew … and I was kind of left with the feeling that it was half defined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The zest that I add for the world on the X Macro pattern is this … and using the same terms as the X Macro wiki page above … instead of …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#define LIST_OF_VARIABLES \
    X(value1) \
    X(value2) \
    X(value3)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… I do this …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#define LIST_OF_VARIABLES(X) \
    X(value1) \
    X(value2) \
    X(value3)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… but when I use it I am a lot more descriptive … and I also group many related things together … to illustrate I will use a familiar if artificial example … in the definition of where I want to gather the related information I define a generator that takes a selector …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#define EVENT_CODE_GENERATOR(SELECTOR) \
    SELECTOR(LeftMouseDown, LBUTTONDOWN, 0x0201) \
    SELECTOR(LeftMouseUp, LBUTTONUP, 0x0202) \
    SELECTOR(LeftMouseDoubleClick, LBUTTONDBLCLK, 0x0203)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… and then when it is used … say to generate an enumeration definition …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#define EVENT_ENUMS(function, message, number) WM_##message=number, 
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;typedef&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;enum&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;EVENT_CODE_GENERATOR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;EVENT_ENUMS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;MaxEventNumber&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Events&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This actually generates this code (ignoring whitespace)…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;typedef&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;enum&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;WM_LBUTTONDOWN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mh&quot;&gt;0x0201&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;WM_LBUTTONUP&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mh&quot;&gt;0x0202&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;WM_LBUTTONDBLCLK&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mh&quot;&gt;0x0203&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;MaxEventNumber&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Events&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… the beauty of this is that the EVENT_CODE_GENERATOR can be reused for many things like generating human readable strings or function definitions for these events … and the SELECTOR parameter can be given a nice name that flows with the code in context around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fuller example can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://godbolt.org/z/QAl4Kv&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Compiler Explorer&lt;/a&gt; or if that is tampered with then on my github repo &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/softwarebear/zestyxmacro.git&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Zesty X Macro Repo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Back in 1994 I came across a technique of generating C++ code through Macros.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Discovered Github Pages, Jekyll, Markdown and Liquid</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/06/09/discovered-liquid.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Discovered Github Pages, Jekyll, Markdown and Liquid" /><published>2018-06-09T13:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-06-09T13:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/06/09/discovered-liquid</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/06/09/discovered-liquid.html">&lt;p&gt;I have been looking around for something that is a bit more flexible than blogger and wordpress … After a bit of consultation with my friends over at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.includecpp.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;#include &amp;lt;C++&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt; I decided to investigate &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; which uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://rubygems.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ruby Gems&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;
 to provide a framework for our masterpieces and powers the local development and final delivery of the pages once published to your default GitHub repo blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pages-themes/midnight&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Midnight theme&lt;/a&gt; as it is clean and the text is very reable … However it didn’t come with a blog by default so I did a bit of googling and found the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/posts/#displaying-an-index-of-posts&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jekyll documentation on posts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I have a blog now … and have gone back and added my other blog posts on here from other sites … have published the site all together and directed people to it. So any posts prior in time to now are from old sites … any after now until a new technology comes along are on this site.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I have been looking around for something that is a bit more flexible than blogger and wordpress … After a bit of consultation with my friends over at #include &amp;lt;C++&amp;gt; I decided to investigate GitHub Pages which uses Ruby Gems and Jekyll to provide a framework for our masterpieces and powers the local development and final delivery of the pages once published to your default GitHub repo blog.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Extract data to Excel compatible clipboard content</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/06/09/Extract-data-to-excel-compatible-paste.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Extract data to Excel compatible clipboard content" /><published>2018-06-09T13:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-06-09T13:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/06/09/Extract-data-to-excel-compatible-paste</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/06/09/Extract-data-to-excel-compatible-paste.html">&lt;p&gt;Small Powershell script to create a table (a TSV) …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$delimiter = &quot;`t&quot;; 

$fileInfo = Get-ChildItem -Recurse | Sort LastWriteTime | SELECT FullName, LastWriteTime 
$fileInfo | ConvertTo-Csv -Delimiter $delimiter | Set-Clipboard
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… the clipboard can now be pasted into Excel and you’ll end up with a nice table you can copy elsewhere, to email for instance, which doesn’t like the CSV/TSV format.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Small Powershell script to create a table (a TSV) …</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My ACCU 2018 Conference</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/04/22/My-ACCU-2018-conference.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My ACCU 2018 Conference" /><published>2018-04-22T14:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-04-22T14:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/04/22/My-ACCU-2018-conference</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/04/22/My-ACCU-2018-conference.html">&lt;p&gt;When I attended the ACCU 2013 conference, I learnt all about the Raspberry Pi in the pre-conference day as I wanted to help my nephew learn more about programming rather than just using a computer. The state education system on computing is a disaster for him and his surrounding years. The Pi has made inroads for school years much younger than him, so I need to help fill in the gaps for him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s as bad now as when I was at school 34 years go, at 14 I had to attend an adult evening class at the local technical college in order to take my ‘O’ level Computer Studies. Back then it was because there were no teachers qualified or able to teach Computing in schools. The same is still true today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2013 Conference had a big Pi focus too, with the first key note from Eben Upton, the founder of the Raspberry Pi Foundation and a lot of focus on educating children with the devices around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unexpectedly, a few years later at work we did a proof of concept for the Tachyon Agent that I’m working on currently to run on a Raspberry Pi, figuring out how to get our codebase compiling and running on this little beauty and what it could do for us. I hadn’t expected that knowledge to come in useful at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately after the conference I was also thrown into upgrading our NightWatchman code base from Visual Studio 2008 to 2013, some deprecations were causing it to fail and there were new ways to do things, mostly lambdas and bindings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the notion of Conference to me was a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I didn’t go back for 5 years. It was way too scary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, this past year has been difficult on a personal level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 35 years working with computers from hobby, through university, intern, quickly becoming senior engineer, team leader, mentor, head of development, reporting the board, switching companies, redundancies, resignations, I found myself back at senior engineer level, more over my opinions and experience had been overruled in the job I had at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had joined the company as a C++/SQL Server database guru, but within a few weeks they had decided I had no say in what they were going to do and ignored me. I stayed for five years as I don’t like quitting, the job had good sides to it. By that time they were just starting to experience the things I predicted they would if they went the route the were choosing at the outset. I received an apology from the person that drove the overriding of my input shortly after I resigned for better things. It was all too late and I have to question the sincerity of that gesture. Maybe they learnt something that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then joined 1E, it was a massive culture shock because of their Agile/TDD approach that I desperately wanted to get into but my previous employer only spoke about but didn’t practise, and I excelled again, quickly earning respect from colleagues, then becoming a team leader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the project I took over as the lead was canned (after three others had tried and left). I was holding the chalice at the time and it pretty much destroyed my self esteem. I was investigated and probed as to what the issues were. The result of the probing was, well, nothing; nothing happened other than I seemed to pushed to one side. No-one told me that I was not to blame, they just didn’t sack me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This destroyed me inside, I was not programming at home, leaving everything at work, I’d lost my mojo, only working 9 hours a day instead of the usual 11, feeling despondent, although still achieving my work goals, churning out good quality code, being a goto guy for others and nurturing others where I could, but I desperately needed nurturing myself. Up to now I had been self reliant as one has to be in startup companies, able to do everything and cope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mid term review in 2017 was horrible, my manager pulled me up on my communication abilities. I went home and boiled with rage over the weekend. Why was I so crap at everything, why was I such a failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I hadn’t listened to what he was really saying to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monday morning I called meetings with HR and my manager and I raged everything through and exposed myself whole-heartedly, a lot of emotions came out that I was really not expecting. Hey I was on the verge of leaving, I had nothing to lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slowly absorbed that my manager was not faulting any of my technical abilities, my drive to do things and finish my tasks. He was challenging me on my relationships with others, that I always seemed to be behind my monitors blocking out the world with my headphones on, that I seemed to not be at the level and exposure that he hoped he would be at in ten years time in his career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is ten years younger than me, but he is wise with it, and I understand he wasn’t being mean to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I have eyesight challenges that manifest in needing to be so close to my monitors that I appear to be hiding behind them and wearing headphones to listen for the noise of the notifications of people trying to contact me because they are out of my field of vision on the screen (see my earlier blog) , and hence appear to be ignoring them. I also do not like bothering other people with my problems. I don’t know why, because I’m totally happy for someone to interrupt me. I can usually pick up the pieces quite quickly afterwards and I love helping people solve their problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just hate exposing the fact that I do not know something myself. Not in a bad way. For instance during a conversation I will happily say I have no experience or knowledge to give a sensible answer and will go away and research it and come back. I don’t bluff or cover up that I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I’m referring to is having a specific problem to solve (or even a series of them if it is a big task on unknown territory) and hitting dead end after dead end, I get too wrapped up in solving the problem, it becomes a personal fight between man and machine, it feels like I’m failing at every turn, only to discover a way through the barrier, only to be hit with another series of failures again. I achieve what I need to do with great elation, which is what keeps me in this job, but I’m disappointed with myself for having taken what feels like so long to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But who am I comparing myself to ? I have no idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to learn to spot this pattern and ask for help much sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also use conditional passive words rather than positive affirmations. I listen too much to that little voice that filters my vocal output, I over analyse what I want to say to point where I don’t say it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my boss was right to challenge me, he was really asking me to grow because he could see something I couldn’t, maybe he used the wrong words at the time, but his heart was in the right place, and I thank him whole heartedly for doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is the mentor I didn’t know I needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recovered the situation a little and my end of year review was on back track, but I still feel I have a lot to learn about myself in this area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I went to Conference as a way of helping myself of exorcise some of these traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To expose your true self takes guts, to put yourself out there as the potential focus of ridicule for those superficial enough to want to take advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are lots of people out there like me, as I’ve come to learn from one of the C++ communities I have joined after discovering them at ACCU 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;www.includecpp.org is a nurturing group for those with some interest in C++ and all other things geeky. it isn’t exclusively C++ focused, to some extent that is our common ground, along with our diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talk about many things from the heart too, how we feel about what is happening to us or around us, topics arise at random as people experience them and are discussed in a respectful way, by those who happen to be around holding the space at the time. It is a diverse group for anyone to join, their three main criteria are that you …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be welcoming&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be kind&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look out for each other&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that the talks that really echoed with me were those where the speakers had overcome some personal struggle or were still dealing with it. It’s easy to talk about technical facts and figures, you just need the right research and references and all is good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me there could be no better values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope I’ll see you there.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">When I attended the ACCU 2013 conference, I learnt all about the Raspberry Pi in the pre-conference day as I wanted to help my nephew learn more about programming rather than just using a computer. The state education system on computing is a disaster for him and his surrounding years. The Pi has made inroads for school years much younger than him, so I need to help fill in the gaps for him.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ACCU 2018 trip report</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/04/22/ACCU-2018-trip-report.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ACCU 2018 trip report" /><published>2018-04-22T13:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-04-22T13:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/04/22/ACCU-2018-trip-report</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/04/22/ACCU-2018-trip-report.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;tuesday---pre-conference-day-2018-04-18&quot;&gt;Tuesday - Pre Conference Day 2018-04-18&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;c-17-in-practice--nicolai-josuttis&quot;&gt;C++ 17 In Practice : Nicolai Josuttis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fast and furious day of new C++ twists and turns, gotchas and interesting observations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing that leapt out for me is that C++ is now on a strict 3 year revision cycle. It might surprise some of the younger readers that I didn’t know that, but prior to ’11 there was an 8 year gap back to ’03, then 5 years back to ’98 and then prior to that there were no international standards, but this means that major churn is happening in the language and we wrinkles need to keep up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end we learned of some deprecations that people working on ’11+’14 need to be aware of, especially when they are deprecated because they didn’t work, not just because they were hard to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the topics were out and out goodness that is already in most compilers today, so you have no excuse not to be learning this stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conference-dates-wednesday-2018-04-11---saturday-2018-04-14&quot;&gt;Conference dates Wednesday 2018-04-11 -&amp;gt; Saturday 2018-04-14&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wednesday&quot;&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;diversity--inclusivity-in-tech--gen-ashley&quot;&gt;Diversity &amp;amp; Inclusivity in Tech : Gen Ashley&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a key note this was an all too short talk on Women in IT and Business in general, mostly showcasing what Gen Ashley is doing to help address the situation and maybe where females could get into STEM business, not to take away from her efforts and success, it said little about how females could stay in the business and progress beyond entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consequently this was followed by a lively series of questions and statements from the audience who I felt were all trying to offer our full support to our female colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a strange one for me, as in most of the companies I have worked for there have always been some strong females role models and 1E, my currently employer, a high proportion of females in the software engineering team and across the company as a whole, it is still not 50/50 but I have the privilege of working with multiple female engineers in all the product teams I’ve worked on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was where I made my first new contact at the conference, as a suggestion I made struck a chord with her too, she congratulated me for saying it and a little group formed around us at the end of the talk to continue on our joint themes. This lead to being introduced to more and more people that she knew over the week and having some engaging conversations, and me joining a another community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fighting-the-controls--daniele-procida&quot;&gt;Fighting the controls : Daniele Procida&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I had attended the day of C++17 which was quite intense (I still haven’t processed it all yet) I decided to try some different topics to feed my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniele’s talk was all about avoiding problems, fault analysis and how we are often misled during these tasks, by drawing a parallel between software engineering and the aerospace industry. Having learnt earlier in my career that it’s the missing pieces in the aftermath of a plane crash that are the important bits in figuring out what went wrong, I felt this would be good talk to attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It didn’t disappoint, the checks and balances that pilots have to go through from initiating the start sequence, take off, flight and landing to turning off the plane are immense. And when something goes wrong, the silly mistakes that we know the pilots have made in trying to resolve the situation, some could have been resolved by them sticking to procedure and just RTFM, or simply telling each other  they are doing and the other acknowledging by repeating what the other just said, a similar experience that we have in pair programming, which I don’t do enough of these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presented main aid to pilots for these situations are books of checklists for certain scenarios that they should follow to diagnose the issue to avoid the pilots panicking and loosing track of reality whilst worrying about killing the 300 passengers sitting behind them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A truly fascinating talk for those who have to deal with customer issues under pressure and those who write complex systems for others to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;playing-with-projections--michel-grootjans&quot;&gt;Playing with Projections : Michel Grootjans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learnt about CQRS and Eventing a long while ago, even before these were a thing, they were a thing. This session was more about insights into what meta data you can get from a simple Event Source as opposed to a database. Historical facts, auditing, rewinding time and spotting bottlenecks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only four people attended, so Michel came to sit with us and get our system building his code base and soon we were all analysing his event stream and spotting the diamonds amongst the rocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michel had lots of different language versions of his app, but strangely no C++ for the ACCU conference, so I built him a C++ version that evening as a thank you for getting me a working Docker .Net Core running on my MacBook so we could build his C# app and rescue my attendance at the session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just wanted to point to something! : Jonathan Müller
Jonathan took us through a proposal, he is building a template library for pointers, so that the our C++ code can be descriptive and more restrictive about what can be done with the pointer like objects. Quite a lot of cram into one talk, the intro was quite condensed but slowly it started to make sense as the talk went on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lightening-talks--various&quot;&gt;Lightening Talks : Various&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 minute talks from lovely experienced and new presenters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one that stood out for me the most was one on Inclusivity and introduced a community that is slowly building a following, #include&amp;lt;C++&amp;gt;, an inclusive nurturing community for those having some interest in C++. The community is open to everyone, the biggest demands being those who can be welcoming, kind and look out for each other. They have a discord server with various other threads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thursday&quot;&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kotlinnative--embracing-existing-ecosystems--hadi-hariri&quot;&gt;Kotlin/Native – Embracing existing ecosystems : Hadi Hariri&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A strange one for a key note, but it was a good introduction and tour of the language. Kotlin seems infinitely flexible, even down to creating new language keywords on the fly, of course showcased all inside JetBrains IDE that make it all that much more easy to work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;finally-executors-for-c--detlef-vollmann&quot;&gt;Finally Executors for C++ : Detlef Vollmann&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three proposals are fighting it out for acceptance in the C++20 standard for the equivalent of promises for futures and asyncs that some might be familiar with already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mocking-frameworks-considered-harmful--peter-sommerlad&quot;&gt;Mocking Frameworks considered, harmful?! : Peter Sommerlad&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter talked us through his views on various mocking frameworks and a home grown alternative, literally. Writing our own thin classes to stand in where we might use the mocking framework. Citing complexities in the macros behind the scenes that make it very hard to figure out what is wrong with the code using the traditional mocking frameworks for C++.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally I don’t find GMock so bad, yes it’s got hideous macros in it behind the scenes, but it does the job and I suspect we’d all end up building our own framework instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;c-countdown-pub-quiz--jon-jagger&quot;&gt;C++ Countdown Pub Quiz : Jon Jagger&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might seem like taking a liberty on work time, but it does help with breaking down the barriers between people and getting to know each other, whilst figuring out how to write the smallest piece of C++ that uses exactly n specific well chosen C++ tokens that will compile using the given compiler (actually hosted in Cyber Dojo).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example you must use tokens ‘include’, ‘this’, ‘—‘, ‘virtual’ and ‘for’. A possible answer is shown to the right but is it the smallest; who knew you could decrement ‘this’, and what does this code do, does it break? Luckily that ‘does it break’ bit wasn’t part of the quiz but is an interesting question. It was exciting, fun and a good way to break down barriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyber Dojo also runs a charity to teach children how to program in far flung lands who otherwise wouldn’t have access to computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lightning-talks--various&quot;&gt;Lightning Talks : Various&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I missed this session because by this point I was struggling with the lack of sleep due to staying up late the other evenings (or actually very early) coding and talking, well for me mostly being a listener, but engaging with the conversations around me where I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides I had to mentally prepare for the dinner too, which is quite an intense experience when one is a socially shy cautious bear at heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conference-dinner&quot;&gt;Conference Dinner&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A truly magical evening hosted by the utterly lovely ACCU Chair, Russel Winder, who held the whole week together perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A chance to reconnect to people I hadn’t spoken to yet from my ACCU 2013 visit and catch up with those I’d spoken to already and making some new contacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each course of the meal is held at a different table and we move around to mix and mingle the conversation, so it involves a lot of introductions and working at talking to each other. There was one awkward moment when the person to my right clearly wanted to ignore me, they and their friend hadn’t moved tables either, a bit of an alpha male love-in against the spirit of the event. It quite shocked him that I offered him and his friend some wine before pouring my own, I think he was expecting me to run away or ignore him back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other people that I spoke to were utterly lovely, and the last table I walked way over to the other side of the room and plonked myself down without looking at who was at the table. Turns out I sat next to the person I connected with at the first key-note and we continued our conversations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;friday&quot;&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-shape-of-a-program--lisa-lippincott&quot;&gt;The Shape of a Program : Lisa Lippincott&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m quite spacial mentally and I’ve always visualised programs in my head as abstract shapes with connections and tunnels, recursions, zips, loops and so on … Lisa is a topological mathematician and presented an interesting view on computer programs and formally describing them in topological terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;linux-userkernel-abi-greg-law&quot;&gt;Linux User/Kernel ABI: Greg Law&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A live kernel debugging session showing how C actually calls into the kernel and how user and kernel modes are protected, the proc filesystem and other intimate details of the layer below the main function and above those system entry points on the stack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;c-today-the-beast-is-back--jon-kalb&quot;&gt;C++ Today: The Beast is Back : Jon Kalb&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This could maybe be titled “C++ from the Beginning to Today”, I suspect we might not have got to the end of what Jon had planned just because of the audience participation, but this is conference and this was a fantastic talk by Jon about the history revolving around C++, why and where it was built, how it has evolved over the intervening period and helped in so many different industries, strange quirks and anecdotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fantastic four coding patterns of Continuous Delivery : Luca Minudel
I had some great hopes for this talk as at the time of writing I’m in the process of doing exactly this to Azure. Unfortunately for me the talk was about someone’s discovery of needing to do CI and CD, rather than pushing the boundaries of the topic, so I ducked out early and switched channel to …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cryptography-for-programmers--daniel-james&quot;&gt;Cryptography for Programmers : Daniel James&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… and learnt a thing or two about the various technologies that I don’t use now, but what particular problem they solved and hence their place in the evolution of cryptographic techniques, why they were compromised and what succeeded them. This helps to decode some of the strange acronyms that revolve around the various algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lightning-talks--various-1&quot;&gt;Lightning Talks : Various&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One talk stood out for me in this line up, one of the speakers stood up and gave an extremely brave talk about his mental breakdown a couple of years back due to the pressures he was under.  To be honest most of the detail of the speech has gone from my head, just the emotion remains, and this reminds me of another community I have grown into over the past 15 years since the death of my previous partner, who have a similar informal evening of sharing from whoever wants to perform whilst away on retreat/holiday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time it was quite a profound speech that moved me to tears, mostly because I very narrowly avoided a similar situation myself so I know how easy it is to happen, but also I have a few friends that have also gone through the same thing, and my own brother took his own life over what I can only assume were acute and chronic work pressures for him, we have no other explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bloomberg-event&quot;&gt;Bloomberg Event&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By now it was obvious to me that I was struggling way too much with talking to people, potentially exposing my weaknesses in front of all these vastly clever intimidating people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t initially planned on attending this event, and there was a clear split in people who weren’t going along and those that were. A guy in the hotel reception pounced on me as I walked through wondering what to do next for the evening and asked whether I would be interested in playing a chess tournament. I replied that I can just about move the pieces in the right directions but was nowhere near able to compete at chess. This didn’t matter he said, it’s just a fun evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was petrified almost, but I went along, I joined in, I moved the pieces, punched the clock, doing something I’ve seen but never done before. I failed with a checkmate at the first round, but hey, 32 people took part in the competition and exposed themselves in front of everyone else, there were about 50 others that didn’t. I achieved a small victory for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later the music started, some of the attendees grabbed guitars and another a laptop and suddenly there was a big jam going on with an computer program being altered live that was controlling all the hardware involved, the laptop screen relayed on a big screen for everyone to see, it was cool man. Some people have awesome talents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More connections made and another successful and late night/early morning, it’s been a while since I’ve survived on three hours sleep a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;saturday&quot;&gt;Saturday&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;creating-an-incremental-architecture-for-your-system--giovanni-asproni&quot;&gt;Creating an Incremental Architecture for your System : Giovanni Asproni&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another great speaker and a reassuring talk on the benefits of an Agile approach to software development. Agile has only came into my working life as a practice since I joined 1E, although I dabbled with eXtreme Programming when I was HoE about 14 years ago at a small company as the notion was first emerging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hackers-guide-to-rust-programming--vigneshwer-dhinakaran&quot;&gt;Hacker’s guide to Rust Programming : Vigneshwer Dhinakaran&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vigneshwer give a us an introduction to Rust, dubbed the Hacker’s guide I was expecting something quite low level and was constantly hearing that Rust is a system programming language, however all the examples that were given were actually quite high level apps, like web sites and file storage. Potentially the improvements they saw were from re-writing the app given the hindsight knowledge they had gained, not re-writing it in Rust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my first insight into Rust, as I had only heard about it at the conference, so I raised the question buzzing around in my head, Vigneshwer had no experience of using Rust at the system level, so it was easy to forgive his skipping lightly over this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily some members of the audience came over to speak to me later after the talk and explained some of the projects they are working on, mostly embedded hardware on micro controllers and they reassured me that Rust certainly is a language that can take you down to the required level, where your app is the operating system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;turtles-hill-climbing-hammers-paper-bags--frances-buontempo&quot;&gt;Turtles! Hill climbing! Hammers! Paper bags! : Frances Buontempo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love Frances’ talks, she has a way of making what I know are vastly complex algorithms and notions simple to take in from the outset. The last talk I attended back in 2013 was on how to program our way out of a paper bag, for which we received certificates. This time it was how to get into the bag and find the cosiest place for our little turtle-bug to reside. The scenarios building to more and more complex models of a paper bag and swarms of ‘turtles’ all trying to solve the problem en-masse using various machine learning techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;software-development--learning-to-walk-again--seb-rose&quot;&gt;Software development – learning to walk again : Seb Rose&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Winding up the conference was Seb’s talk essentially about being Agile in the software industry because we don’t know what is around the next corner. Recounting the tales of a recent solo walking trip in the south of France, the big plans he made in anticipation of the excursion that became smaller and smaller as holiday time approached and realities kicked in, then mishaps along the way that caused changes of plans and adapting to the resources in the environment surrounding him when necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;in-conclusion&quot;&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wonderful close for me, as this was pretty much my experience of the conference, not what I planned beforehand, and many re-plannings along the way, and I failed to hold back the tears from the warmth and love I felt from everyone in the room for the ups and downs we get along the road in our software engineering careers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Tuesday - Pre Conference Day 2018-04-18</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding what I can see</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/10/19/understanding-what-i-can-see.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding what I can see" /><published>2017-10-19T15:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-10-19T15:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/10/19/understanding-what-i-can-see</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/10/19/understanding-what-i-can-see.html">&lt;p&gt;I often struggle to explain to people what I can see in what situations, so the best way to explain this is to show you is with some pictures that I have created that describe what I see in various situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The eye conditions that I have are :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bilateral moderate myopia
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;short sighted in both eyes&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bilateral congenital cataracts
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;born with cataracts in both eyes, a problem to do with development of the eyes of the foetus in the womb.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;in left eye the cataract is central, causing spatial distortions and rendering the eye useless for reading or anything except peripheral vision&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;in the right eye the cataract is off to one side so does not cause the spatial distortions&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deprivational Amblyopia / Lazy left eye
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;because of the central cataract my left eye didn’t develop normally&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;this is better known as causing double vision.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bilateral pigment dispersion syndrome
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the iris colouring is falling off, floating into the eye and blocking the draining canal, which builds up the pressure, which leads to glaucoma.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;moderate myopics are more prone to this apparently.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many situations that my eyesight causes me problems, but as I spend most of my time in front of a computer, I’ll start with that one … the others will appear as time goes by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;at-my-desk&quot;&gt;At my desk&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent a little bit of time putting together some images to help illustrate how it affects my day to day job … it’s not a huge impact … but it has some consequences that I do endeavour to work around and appear to be as ‘normal’ as possible … even though I’m very much at the thin end of that bell curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/img/eyes/raw-screenshot-area-of-focus.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;img-large-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My monitor set up is two 24inch wide-screen monitors (DELL U2414M) lying horizontally but the pair aligned vertically centred to the middle of my right eye. I sit with my right eye vertically in the middle of my upper monitor about 3/4 of the way down the screen if I look straight ahead with my eyes. My eye is about 20cm away from the screen at the nearest point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve captured the screens without any effects (apart from obscuring sensitive information), I believe is what you would see if you could see both screens in focus all at the same time … I don’t know whether that is what 20/20 vision people are able to see when they look at their monitors … maybe someone could comment … I appreciate that our brain focuses on a small area and the rest becomes blurred to some extent … but how much others can see and read at once without moving their eyes from the focussed area I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to show you what I can see if I focus on the token ‘printerName’ highlighted in the code snipped in the image above with a yellow eliptical(-ish) highlight on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/img/eyes/left-eye-only.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;img-large-left&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/img/eyes/right-eye-only.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;img-large-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I close one eye at a time and [try to] look at the word ‘printerName’ in that yellow highlighted area … the two pictures below show what I can see with my eyes individually if I try to take in the whole picture without moving my eye. The white and blue areas in the lower screen really become solid blocks of white with a blue line above … but I can vaguely make out that it is not solid colour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having seen both eyes separately, you obviously know that our brains will attempt to combine the images from both eyes into one 3D view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/img/eyes/what-i-can-see.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;img-large-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if I open both eyes and try to view the screens normally then I see something similar to this with my brain …  the distortion that I get with the left eye comes and goes depending on how long I’ve been looking at the screen … it is there when I initially look at the monitor and fades out the longer I concentrate on the text with my right eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do see two images that do not align and I mostly notice this on the left hand side (when I look towards my nose with my right eye)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A reason I wear headphones a lot … imagine notifications popping up in the far corners of the screens … or for Skype for Busiess which seems to popup in the background behind other windows … that’s why I don’t see them … but I can hear them if I wear the headphones.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I often struggle to explain to people what I can see in what situations, so the best way to explain this is to show you is with some pictures that I have created that describe what I see in various situations.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Google Chrome preferences file exposes your browsing history</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2016/05/02/google-chrome-preferences-file-exposes-your-browsing-history.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google Chrome preferences file exposes your browsing history" /><published>2016-05-02T12:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-05-02T12:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2016/05/02/google-chrome-preferences-file-exposes-your-browsing-history</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2016/05/02/google-chrome-preferences-file-exposes-your-browsing-history.html">&lt;p&gt;So there’s been a few emails circulating recently about Internet Explorer and Edge exposing your private browsing history and horror of horrors not being on our side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well how many of you have thought that Chrome was immune to this … ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a look inside your Preferences file …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;C:\Users\&amp;lt;username&amp;gt;\AppData\Local\Google\Chrome\User Data\Default\Preferences
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… search for bits of your favourite website url inside this file … chances are you will find it embedded in there somewhere … along with it’s friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearing your browser history cache of urls and such makes no difference to the content of this file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The file also contains a mysterious section at the bottom … encrypted … would love to know what’s in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will need to kill ALL running Chrome instances in order to be able to successfully (and permanently) delete this file … don’t worry … it doesn’t seem to make much difference to your browsing experience (including passwords etc)… it’s just the dodgy urls are now gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the file returns within a few seconds and you haven’t launched Chrome … you didn’t kill them all before you deleted the file … this new file will have your urls in it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not sure when they are written to this file though … or if they still are … but they seem to be historical from other machines on which I use Chrome with the same google account.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">So there’s been a few emails circulating recently about Internet Explorer and Edge exposing your private browsing history and horror of horrors not being on our side.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reducing code friction in mixed C and C++ cross platform projects</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2014/06/24/reducing-code-friction.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reducing code friction in mixed C and C++ cross platform projects" /><published>2014-06-24T19:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-06-24T19:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2014/06/24/reducing-code-friction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2014/06/24/reducing-code-friction.html">&lt;p&gt;So I’ve just inherited a very new project where part of the code is written in C and C++, a language I loved but put on the back burner about 12 years ago whilst I concentrated on C# … I have kept up to date with it (C++11)  … but it has amazed me how slooooow it is to develop code on this platform … much slower than I remember … especially when there is no code discipline in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the code I have inherited looks like it was written about 20 years ago … rather than last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This frustrates me a lot as it’s just lack of software crafting discipline that has got it into this state so quickly and resulted in code that is so viscous it’s unbelievable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things that we will be doing to help loosen the code up a bit :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unicode&quot;&gt;Unicode&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decide on your standard for text interchange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UTF8 seems to be the most portable form across the various platforms we use (Win/Mac/Linux).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;wchar_t changes size similarly to int, fantastic !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are new types to combat this, std::u16string and std::u32string … which may or may not be equivalent to std::wstring … depending on your platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;strings&quot;&gt;Strings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;std::basic_string&amp;lt;&amp;gt; is heavenly to most C++ programmers … but those C lovers have their arrays of characters … why would you need anything else … ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe to avoid dealing with malloc and free or global statics with their threading issues, etc ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;premature-optimising&quot;&gt;Premature Optimising&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C/C++ dudes love optimising … even extending it to the source code … boy the compiler must be grateful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the point of making something super optimal if it is only going to execute once per run or maybe a few times … rather than billions of times per run … prefer readable clear code and classes with nice encapsulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;extern-c&quot;&gt;Extern “C”&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an abomination these days … you only need this to talk to old libraries that you can’t compile any more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prefer using .cpp files and compiling them with a C++ compiler, you get a better language environment and don’t have to keep writing layers of crap to translate C++ down to C … I thought you liked to optimise things ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;resharper&quot;&gt;Resharper&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve learnt a lot from the C# world, one tool that is slowly moving into the C++ world is Resharper … heaven sent … this product can currently navigate your code brilliantly … it makes an attempt to do the other stuff that Resharper is excellent at … it’s still in development … has some rough edges … but given the amount I rely on this tool in C# … it will be my best friend forever if they complete the C++ side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please give this tool your support … give it a try … feedback your findings to JetBrains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;posix&quot;&gt;Posix&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you write your system stuff with OS specific stuff and partition it off to separate platforms or use std stuff as much as possible ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This depends on what you need to do obviously, but it becomes hard to keep all the builds in sync.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;macros&quot;&gt;Macros&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to avoid macros … especially with C++ templates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Absolutely no need for macros any more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about xplatform stuff though … easy … divide your libraries up into generic and OS specific parts … declare everything in the generic … define most of your stuff in the generic library … define the specific stuff twice for each platform … this forces you to think more about doing it and whether you can avoid it … rather than just using a MACRO sledgehammer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leaves the code clean and readable … not in a nested spaghetti of #ifdefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;solid-principles&quot;&gt;SOLID Principles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes these apply to C++ too … oh yes they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tdd--unit-testing&quot;&gt;TDD / Unit Testing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get hold of a good Unit Testing library (GoogleTest, CppUnit … there’s lots of them).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Write unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preferably before your implement anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simples.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">So I’ve just inherited a very new project where part of the code is written in C and C++, a language I loved but put on the back burner about 12 years ago whilst I concentrated on C# … I have kept up to date with it (C++11) … but it has amazed me how slooooow it is to develop code on this platform … much slower than I remember … especially when there is no code discipline in place.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This is me</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2014/06/07/this-is-me.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This is me" /><published>2014-06-07T15:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-06-07T15:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2014/06/07/this-is-me</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2014/06/07/this-is-me.html">&lt;p&gt;Hello !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So .. finally I have succumbed to the blogging fever … or maybe I’ve just realised that I’ve got a lot of stuff to say that can help others down the road of becoming a fantastic software engineer / crafter or happier human being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little bit about me … each topic is a thread … going through things almost in chronological order …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;big-red-gay-panda-bears&quot;&gt;Big Red Gay Panda Bears&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was born in the middle of the summer of 1970 very close to the middle of England. Technically I guess this means I was conceived in the 1960s, this might explain my musical tastes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first major revelation I had about the age of five was that I realised that I liked other boys in ways that I didn’t like girls (I liked being with girls, I don’t mean that) … and quickly learnt this wasn’t how everyone else felt and that I needed to hide it … I spent the next 13 years hiding it … which was extremely hard … missing out on the childhood relationships simply because it would not have been allowed by my parents or the populous of the small town I grew up in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 18 I decided I’d had enough hiding so I branched down the path of being myself and stuff what everyone else wants me to be … I told my best friend … he was fine with it … I told more people … they weren’t so fine … lost a lot of ‘friends’ … found new ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 19 my mum found out, went ballistic, she and my brother ganged up on me to ‘turn me straight’ … Dad was never told … I complied whilst at home … desperate to get back to University … [from the frying pan into the fire unfortunately].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/img/red%20panda%20face%20on.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;img-small-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a big hairy guy … hence the “bear” in my pseudonym … as we gays love to label everything … there are otters, cubs, foxes and all sorts of things … but I’m most definitely a bear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always loved teddy bears and real life bears … in fact if you want to get a feel for how much I love the cuteness of bears … here are some pictures of a red panda … if I could be a real bear … this is what I would be … because they are so damned cute … and so am I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Damn it … I just want to stare at those pictures now … stop it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to get this out in the open right now … upfront … you might see as me ‘shouting it from the rooftops’ to quote my brother … but it is what I am … it touches everything I do … I cannot turn it off … as a poster I saw recently in Soho said … “Some dinosaurs are gay, get over it !”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes … it really is you that needs to get over it … move on with your life … if you find it hard to accept a non-straight person as an equal … and you don’t want to try … then don’t bother talking to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;glasses&quot;&gt;Glasses&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other major thing you’ll notice about me is that I wear glasses … I have done since I was 9 months old … I was born with bilateral congenital cataracts … astigmatism and short sightedness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was knocked down by a van when I was 3 years old because I didn’t see it when I ran out into the road … I also probably didn’t understand that was not a good idea at the time … broke a leg … lucky to be alive I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mum had cataracts … her brother has it … my mysterious maternal grand-father had it … our family tree has been studied by someone at Edinburgh University … some like my mum have been operated on (she has lived most of her life with no lenses in her eyes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something to do with genes … according to my family tree some great-great-great-great-great relative decided to marry and have kids … and then suddenly he appears to be marrying someone from a newer generation of the same family (most likely a niece but I haven’t found the exact biological relationship yet)… my genes incorporating that branch&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My brother … he didn’t get it … and believed that he was free from any problems and that his children were perfect and didn’t need to be checked by a fully qualified optician like I did … that’s a shame because one of his kids spent years unable to see properly at school before he was hit by a bicycle in the street and people realised he couldn’t see well enough … I did tell him when he came to visit the my house one time that his child couldn’t see properly because he was using his feet to judge the distance down a step and hesitating more than he should have done at that age … just like I do now … no his children were perfect and didn’t need to … who knows … they might have caught the gay gene too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look into my eyes you’ll see wide pupils … no I’m not on cocaine … I’m on atropine … this widens my iris to let more light in around the cataract so that I can see … but it lets too much light in .. that’s why I wore very dark glasses as a child … and everyone thought I was blind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to stop using atropine a few years ago … as it’s not the most friendly drug to be taking constantly … after two weeks the pain in my eyes was unbearable …  I think it was from the inability to see rather than withdrawal symptoms … :-) … ho hum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever been to an opticians (I mean a real one, not Specsavers) .. then you’ll often be given a few drops in your eyes that feel like your eyes are being dissolved out of their sockets …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/img/red%20panda%20in%20tree.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;img-small-left&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effect of those drops last a few hours at most … the same dose of atropine lasts about a week for me … my pupils contract fully within a few minutes and slowly release over that week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then if you’re really lucky they shine a bright light in your eyes for far too long to have a look at what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I wear a big hat that blocks the sun … and try to use more everyday looking glasses … news flash … there are no sunglasses that work  … obliterating the sun with a hat or turning my back on it or moving to the shade is the only effective option I have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m still likely to walk straight past you in the street as though I ignored you … because I have to concentrate where I’m putting my feet and take in the environment around me … and avoid you rather than run into you … so please forgive me … once I get used to your general height / weight / colour / shape / dress sense I will be able to recognise you just the same as anyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does have advantages … I can stare at my monitors all day completely naturally because they are positioned exactly where my eyes need them to be … it looks a bit odd to others … but my eyes are probably under far less strain than your own because I’m so aware of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes I could have my cataracts removed … but surgeons don’t believe I would see any better anyway … and I could lose my eyesight through surgery risks anyway … I’d rather not be blind if I can help it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My childhood surgeon advised me to wait as long as possible before I had any operation so that I would benefit form technological advances in lens implant technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However so at age 45 I instigated investigations in doing this … only to be told by another surgeon that these days they operate on babies to avoid the problem of the nerve/brain developing incorrectly around the visual cortex … in other words they could remove the lense but it’s likely it’ll make no difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means I cannot drive a vehicle because I cannot see the number plate at the required distance … I cannot see too well with my left eye … which means I have to be based near public transport for home, work and play … but I’d also kill people on the road driving a car because my eyes don’t react to things quickly enough … so no removal for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have recently also been diagnosed with Pigment Dispersion Syndrome, this means that my iris now is starting to lose its coloured cells which float off and block up the drainage channels in the eye, causing the internal pressure to increase, which causes glaucoma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roll on Google Car … but I guess one will still need to be able to drive just in case they go berserk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;atheism&quot;&gt;Atheism&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to three levels of Catholic schools from 4 to 16 … about 7 I decided I really didn’t believe all this god stuff … the words in the prayers and hymms weren’t my words … I saw religion causing mass problems around the world … terrorism from the various factions in the Northern Ireland ‘Troubles’ hiding behind their gods, priests, fathers and vicars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look … if you don’t believe my god you are going to go to hell … if I don’t believe in your god then I am going to hell … we have just condemned every living human to an eternity in hell … regardless of which god you believe in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/img/red%20panda%20tongue.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;img-small-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ergo there is no point believing in god … when you’re dead you’re gone … kaput … nothing … but the molecules/atoms/particles/waves/branes you borrowed whilst nature assembled them into a human form will live on in the universe for eternity doing their job elsewhere … thank you for the loan of them, universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I’m really extremely lucky some of my borrowed particles might pass through a Red Panda one day … wouldn’t that be cool … assuming we haven’t killed them all with pollution or for food as we fight to stay alive on a planet too small for us to expand into .. because we waste time and resources on wars because of our religious beliefs .. rather than building a spaceship to transport us to remote planets to stop us being wiped out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stop wasting your time in church or on the battlefield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;computers&quot;&gt;Computers&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About the age of thirteen I became interested in computers … this is when the BBC Micro was all over the television in the UK and Sunday mornings were extremely boring because that was when I was supposed to be being a good christian and going to church … because there literally was nothing else to do because the country shut down on a Sunday … but the open university had a joint venture with the BBC to get the country using computers … and had a TV programme on Sunday mornings … it suddenly became the most interesting hour of the week for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our school had two of them … and a Research Machines RM380Z … and a teleprinter … and a modem … that could call Janet … and a maths teacher … Miss Lynne Jones … who in her spare time ran a computer club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to thank you Miss Jones (Lynne I would like to call you but I haven’t seen you since I last visited school over 20 years ago now and you no longer work there) … you opened my eyes to the world of computing … spent time helping a kid learn something fantastic … and you set me down the path from which I made my life what it is … I’ve never had a moment where I have wanted to give up doing what I do and do something else instead … I’ve never had a day of work despite working in computing for 20 years … computers are my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also defended me once against a few bullies at school who thought they were better than the fat blind kid … a trait I now have in bucket loads … and strive for fairness and equality for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;software&quot;&gt;Software&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got my first computer at 14 … a BBC Micro Model B … and started learning how to program … I used to write lots of graphing programs to help me plot the curves for my maths homework … this turned into writing drawing programs … both bitmap and vector based … I got some joysticks and made those work with the drawing programs … then I got a mouse … and disk drives … started writing bespoke database applications … file systems … machine code … learning more and more stuff about the world of computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to pay tribute to my brother at this point … he was instrumental in persuading my father to allow me to spend 75% of my life savings to that point on computer … and he added £50 leaving my father only needing to supply the other £50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My brothers argument at the time was that if I did get into the field of computing then I’d be sorted for life money wise … so it was worth the risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this time I was already dismantling electronic things to see what was inside … putting them back together again … and they worked … I think Dad found that a bit scary that I might spend more money on anything he’d ever bought for himself only to break it … and he had no clue how to fix it if I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if my brother hadn’t stuck up for me to be treated very differently to the way he himself had been treated … forced to get work rather than go to college .. then I also probably wouldn’t be writing this blog today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took an ‘O’ level in computer studies at the local technical college on tuesday evenings … because my school couldn’t teach the ‘O’ level because Miss Jones only had an ‘O’ level in computing herself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I passed that at the age of 15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then went to sixth form to do Maths, Physics and Computer Studies ‘A’ levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t been taught a high enough level in maths and physics at school … when my teachers suggested that I shouldn’t go to college to do Maths … and I guess I didn’t realise that at the time … but I got in probably because I knew more about computers than my teachers at the time … I struggled with Physics greatly … mostly because I didn’t know enough Maths … i dropped Physics ‘A’ level for a year and took an ‘O’ level in it instead whilst doing the other two … then in the second year my Maths was up to scratch … so I started the ‘A’ level Physics and took an ‘AO’ in Electronics too … so after three years I had my three ‘A’ levels, an ‘O’ in Physics and an ‘AO’ in Electronics too.
I also started to hear about the mystery illness that was killing gay people … AIDS they called it … all sounded very scary … doom from god on the gays … well see above about how much notice I took of that opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physics should be compulsory education in place of any kind of religious studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 18 I got my hands on an eprom image of an early C programming language implementation the Beeb … my first taste of the real world of programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;life-death-friends-and-lovers&quot;&gt;Life, Death, Friends and Lovers&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this time all four grandparents were dead … I’d only known three of them anyway … I was the youngest in my generation … my father was a third generation only child … my mother didn’t talk to her side of the family … I grew up with my older brother really … so we were pretty isolated apart from a few close family friends … everyone remarked how mature and grown up I was … I think that comes with not leading the idillic childhood experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then my life has been tinged by various deaths over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My father was a hard working man … I think this is where I get it from … for most of his life before I was born he was a carpenter and joiner … buying a house for us to live in and support the family was a struggle … and then he started to get ill regularly … the doctors discovered that he was allergic to cedar wood … a common material in construction of houses … the area where he worked … so he had to give up his job … luckily he knew someone who worked at Jaguar cars … so from around the time I was born he was working as a quality control and car dispatch driver … giving the cars a final quality check upon leaving the production line and driving the cars around to the parking area where they then went off to be collected for distribution to their final destinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember him working nights … weekends … days … throughout it we always had enough to eat … and we owned our own home … slowly slowly we started to gain extra luxuries … we bought a second hand caravan and upgraded the car to pull it when I was about 6 … then we used that caravan about 20 times a year going away for weekends and the usual week or two week holidays when the factory closed with the Jaguar Caravan and Camping Club … very cheap holidays … but still we had to choose wisely which holiday we were doing each year … we hardly ever bought ready made sandwiches at a supermarket … once I remember eating out at a cafe and I don’t ever remember going to a restaurant with my parents other than for my brothers wedding … when we got a fridge for the kitchen … I was about 16 … we got a colour television … I was 18 … and no … this wasn’t in the 1960s … it was the late 1980s … it was 1994 when my mum got a telephone installed … after dad died and I managed to convince her she could afford it … we didn’t have a lot of money to splash around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just before my final year exams at University my father died … he had seen me start my career in computing at Hewlett Packard during my third year thick sandwich degree placement … earning roughly the same salary as he did … at that time he was earning the highest salary he’d ever earnt in his life at the time … so my brothers predictions were already bearing fruit … a year later I started another job on 1.5 times his salary … I now lived in a different world to my humble upbringing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember the last physical contact we had was him proudly shaking my hand as he said goodbye just after dropping me off for my last full term at university and me feeling that I just wanted to hug him … but don’t ever remember ever having done so … often I’d spent the hour long journey silently crying in the back of the car at the despair of having to go back to the living hell for another ten weeks … but the third year was the happiest and best of the lot … some of the idiots around me had finally grown up and were not afraid to talk to me for fear of being labelled as gay themselves … some of them had finally experienced death themselves … it puts life into perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/img/red%20panda%20and%20cub.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;img-small-left&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My father had a heart attack brought on by the sarcoidosis he acquired from wood dust … he went into hospital for a few days …  finally he had another heart attack that finished him off … the next day my brother knocked on my door at university … I opened the door and was surprised … he just stood there … there was no other reason for him to be there … I looked at him and said … “Dad’s dead isn’t he?” … he just collapsed weeping into my arms and we stood hugging and crying for a while …. with me re-assuring him that everything would be ok … apparently no-one wanted to bother me at uni with the news that my father was dying … he must have been wondering why the hell I wasn’t visiting him in hospital … it was because nobody told me Dad … I couldn’t phone home because we didn’t have a telephone … but they could have contacted me very easily … the hall had pay phones … the university staff knew where I lived … they just didn’t want me there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year or so after finishing University, I met the first people I ever met who i knew to be HIV+ … I am still in awe of their bravery in the face of adversity … and how easily they managed to get hold of cannabis too … by this time I was living in Oxford with my first partner … they were his friends from way back … Pat and Nigel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About this time the probate had been sorted from Dad’s will … and to my complete surprise he had left me a small sum of money through his life insurance … about £4000… that money went into a bank … but shortly after I used it as part of a deposit on a house I bought in Maidenhead with my partner at the time … boy that was a scary thing to do … and suddenly I was all growed up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mother and brother came to view the house I bought and dissed the place immediately … saying I’d done a stupid thing … hating the house completely … also I think they were pissed off that I was living with a guy … cus a few years earlier they’d both ganged up on me to try to bully me into being straight when they found out I was gay after mum rifled through my stuff when I was out working one day … and here I was being gay again … how very dare you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I later sold the house for nearly three times what I bought it for … so I don’t think I did a bad job. I think the biggest problem was that I bought the house for twice the price my brother paid for their house … and nearly 40 times the price of my parents house when they bought theirs … it was a reality check for them on the cost of living where I needed to live in order to work in the job I wanted to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway Pat and Nigel were the sweetest guys alive … clearly loved each other to bits … I got to know them fairly well and joined their circle of friends … coincidentally they had lived in Maidenhead before Oxford … not far from where I bought the house … Nigel died a few years after I met them … Pat carried on for about five more years after that … but I only saw him once during that time … he didn’t really want to be seen … but I remember our last time together we great fondness … lots of hugs and warmth … they were crazy dudes and I love them and miss them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pat died in 2003 … the same year as my uncles partner … and another mutual friend of Pat and Nigel fame I found out after the event at a random party I had been invited to … and the same year my second partner of three years … David … also died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was the biggest head fuck I’ve ever had … woke up in the morning … kissed him goodbye and went to work … phoned him at lunch time and realised that he was about to have an epileptic fit … I could always tell when he was going to have one … but they only happened about once every six months or so  … tried to make him as safe as possible before it happened … I got into the habit of talking to him and telling him he was about to have a fit and that everything was ok … even though he couldn’t answer me … his eyes seemed to communicate with me and show me he trusted me to do my best to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A colleague at work drove me home after hearing me try to talk David out of the fit … when we got there David was in the bedroom … clearly just recovering from the fit he had alone … the whole process would take about an hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stayed with him a little while till he was lucid and normal again … then stupidly I went back to work with my colleague … stupid stupid fucking stupid bear … never let work become so consuming that you do stuff like that … when I got home David was dead and my world crumbled into mush whilst I went through the process of sorting out the funeral … helping his mum and sister cope … helping myself cope … trying to stop my mum and brother trying to persuade me to be heterosexual again (not for the first time) … picking up his ashes from the funeral home (they weigh a ton … don’t be fooled by the stuff on the telly) … attending the inquest into his death … spreading his ashes around Grenfell Park in Maidenhead one full moon night … David loved sitting in the park watching the world go by after he came back from work and college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was so scared to tell me he had epilepsy … I remember the phone calls at the start of our short distance relationship before he moved in … I reassured him it was not a problem and immediately went out and bought a load of books on epilepsy (the internet still wasn’t brilliant then) … I knew more than he wanted to know by the end of those … I still didn’t spot the signs of his first fit in my presence … that was fucking scary … the first time I saw someone stop breathing and go blue … it wasn’t the last time I saw him fit … each time it happened was slightly different and scary but with common elements … only once did I call for an ambulance because he had three fits in a row … the last time I saw him not breathing and blue was different … he was cold and stiff … face down on the kitchen floor … when I eventually managed to roll him over and attempt CPR as the person on the phone was instructing me to … I could tell from his eyes that he was gone … he never started breathing and didn’t turn pink that time … that was the start of the chaos into which my personal life descended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love you David … and although I have forgiven myself … I still find the world empty without you sometimes … mostly when I look at your picture … which happens fairly frequently … I seem to remember something about you and smile every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four people I knew very well had died in the space of four months … fuck me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s when I found a fantastic organisation called the Edward Carpenter Community … they pretty much pieced me back together over the space of a week … I’ll never forget the first hug I got on that first week … I guess the person that gave it to me won’t forget it either … thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 8 years earlier … I met a guy in The Jolly Farmers … a gay pub in Oxford … who is degreed up to his eye balls in Physics … can animate theories just by speaking and waving his arms around … and as gay as a goose … told me about an organisation that whisks a bunch of guys away to the lake district to have a gay old time for a week … it sounded fantastic but I never looked into it … this was whilst I was working in Didcot Parkway at my first job after graduating … this guy works at the Rutherford Appleton labs … he gave me his email address … it ended in @rl I recall (or something equally strange to how they are today) … that’s a really old dns domain from the Janet network … a reminder from my school days of that modem that could call Janet … the organisation he told me about turned out to be the same Edward Carpenter Community and we did eventually enjoy a week at the same event together but he didn’t remember me yet was surprised I knew stuff about him that he’d told me that fascinated me and I’d remembered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a new family in the ECC … and I attended a total of about 8 week holidays with them … I co-organised three holidays with two other men for a group of 30 men up in the Wastwater youth hostel … by way of returning something back to the organisation that had helped me cope at a very dark period of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 years ago (2010) on good friday (bad friday as it turned out) my brother committed suicide … still have no idea why … he would talk to me about stuff … but it was never anything deep and meaningful … he had a huge difficulty with me being gay … even though I could make him see that his logic was flawed … he still persisted in his belief that really I should be straight and get married … he never left the backwards little town I grew up in for anything more than a holiday here and there and to commute to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He died quite dramatically about 10ish in the morning … was flown to hospital … lots of drama … hang on for a few hours … then died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mother called my uncle the next day … to tell him what had happened … unbeknownst to my mother … both my uncles were staying with Orlando and me to visit the Ideal Home exhibition the following day … my uncle told me immediately what my mother had just told him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I said … “the selfish cunt” … because the first thing that spring to mind was the kids and his wife and instantly re-living the aftermath of David dying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mother did not tell me my brother had died until the day afterwards. I could have travelled up to be by his bedside to make a difference had anyone bothered to tell me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I miss you Andrew … really I do … I never stopped loving you despite you driving me almost insane … in two years I will be the older brother … that is a very strange feeling … I’ll look out for my nephews too … one of which also seems to want to work in the software industry … I’ll do my best to guide him down a good path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I went to the wedding of my brother’s wife to a new guy … life carries on … I wish the new family unit well and will remain friends with my now ex-sister-in-law and her new family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blimey … that topic was a big one … and rightly so … life and death are important events … don’t be consumed by work … know when to go home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;taekwon-do&quot;&gt;TaeKwon-Do&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In parallel with starting college I also started learning TaeKwon-Do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest the reasons for doing so were initially a bit dubious.
A son of a guy that owned the local corner shop (that closed on thursday afternoons and sundays because of a god) who was probably ten years older than me … was amazingly cute … and red hair … terribly straight … and a black belt 2nd dan in TaeKwon-do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A guy I went to school with attended the same classes as the shop guy … he was cute too … so was his brother I soon discovered … both were green belts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/img/tagb%20instructors.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;img-small-left&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I went along to see what they got up to … found out that I was taking lessons from Grand Master Dave Oliver (now a 9th Dan, he’s the guy directly underneath the DO in the picture) … a world renowned instructor who just happened to come teach TKD at the school I had just left for college in my backwards home town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My brother tried it for a very brief period too … he didn’t like it as much as I did … I think he got his yellow tag but gave up after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After five years on and off I became a red belt in TaeKwon-Do (two grades from ‘black belt’)… the reason I stopped is because I had dislocated both shoulders and had my nose smashed in by this point … also it was difficult to attend regularly as I was moving around so much and public transport is not good in ‘rural’ places like Loughborough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love martial arts … asia … the beautiful people that have roots in that land … and stocky butch guys that I wouldn’t have thought for a moment could possibly be gay like me … because gays were effeminate and weak as far as my social environment and mother and brother kept telling me … how wrong they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;bear-iversity&quot;&gt;Bear-iversity&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst in my third year at college I started applying for Universities … as I knew I would need a degree to do it … there was no-where for a public transport bound bear cub to work locally … I wouldn’t have been able to get an apprenticeship or get a job without experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I visited Loughborough once through a visit to an afternoon of Physics lectures … and when I went back to visit it for an overnight prospective student visit to try it out … I really liked the place … very green and open campus … lots of space … and plenty of room for students to live on campus … no need to travel anywhere … lots of nice eye candy playing rugby and tennis as I recall … perfect for an almost blind gay bear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I applied and was successful … I lived in Telford Hall for three years and my life there was complete hell … I couldn’t have chosen a University filled with more homophobic students if I tried … except maybe one of those religious places 8-).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the gay people there were hostile … I was a big fat hairy bear … the bear scene didn’t exist then … and I didn’t fit in cause I wasn’t young, thin and beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the living hell I endured in halls … I scraped through with a First Class Honours degree in Computing … at least I had a goal to achieve to get me away from my tiny ‘everyone knows everyone’ home town and the even worse fellow small brained students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to thank the few real friends I made at Loughborough who got me through uni and the period after my father died … some are lost in the mists of time … some I keep a vague contact through Facebook or Google+ … we all have such busy lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So at uni I learnt far too much group theory maths and AI … logical circuitry … but best of all … C  &amp;amp; C++.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At HP I learnt about QA … something that has been the backbone of my career since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;cooking&quot;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From about the age of eleven I remember cooking breakfast for mum and myself before I cycled off to school … full blown porridge, omelettes, bacon, beans, toast (not all at once) … not just milk and cereals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prefer to spend the time constructing a meal from it’s components rather than buy a ready made meal … I loathe spending money on restaurants … which I do go to fairly frequently now … I’d much rather buy really good unusual ingredients and make something nice myself and it still cost less than eating it in a restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;coming-up-to-date&quot;&gt;Coming up to date&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I currently live in London with my life partner of nearly ten years standing … my lovely Orlando … we met in Cardiff on the gay scene over there … which is lovely … much nicer and friendlier than London … although London is starting to pull it’s head out of it’s arse and realise that we are all part of the same family … or maybe I’m just getting older and going to different places where people are more friendly anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orlando is a lovely man … extremely hard working … and totally dedicated to helping others … he’s currently an Accident and Emergency nurse in central London and loving every minute of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are home birds mostly … we really enjoy living together and couldn’t be any more happier … except for winning the lottery … which we don’t play very often as we never win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re on our third property … moving from Maidenhead to Reading and now to London … commuting has become very expensive … and we’d rather spend the money on fun things and have more time together than train fares and commuting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a lovely petite cat … Angel … who occasionally comes to us for some love … but she is mostly a free spirit … except when she’s hungry … she has a lovely boyfriend who occasionally pops around for tea and a chat … we did think she was lesbian for a while … but we do approve of Cimba … he’s quite chunky and very cute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I currently work for 1E … this is the first company I have worked for that has taken the radical very latest approaches to software engineering and run with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I have learnt all about Test Driven Development and it has totally changed the way I write software.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Hello !</summary></entry></feed>